A Guide to the Papers of The Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry 1934-2001
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
The Papers of The Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry 1934-2001
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-8
23.5 linear feet, (53 boxes, 23,000 items.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Papers were collected by Dr. Barbara Brodie and the University of Virginia School of Nursing. The Papers of JoAnne Peach were donated by JoAnne Peach.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry (CNHI), established at the University of Virginia in 1991 to support historical scholarship in nursing, is dedicated to the preservation and study of nursing history in the United States. The goals of the Center include the collection of materials, the promotion of scholarship, and the dissemination of historical research findings.
Scope and Content
The Center for Nursing Historical Inquiry archive includes 16 subcollections. Sixteen collections are located in this EAD. NAPNAP, MS-20, has it's own EAD guide. Subcollections include Association of State and Territorial Directors of Nursing Papers (ASTDN), 1985-2001 (Boxes 1-4 ), Evelyn Crary Bacon Papers, 1942-1991 (Boxes 1-2), Alice Burford Booth Papers, 1940-1967 (Boxes 1-2), Dr. Barbara Brodie Papers (Box 1), Rose Marie Chioni Papers, 1940-1967 (Boxes 1-3), Annie Laurie Crawford Papers, 1934-1987 (Boxes 1-3), Kathryn Jaquette Papers, 1969-1974 (Boxes 1-3), Louise Paris Jones Papers, 1946-1998 (Boxes 1-4), Gloria Nuckles Papers, 1950-1954 (Box 1), Gretchen Osgood Papers, 1963-1990 (Boxes 1-3), JoAnne Peach Papers, 1962-2001 (Boxes 1-8), SERPN collection (Boxes 1-12), Levato Jacobs Thomas Papers, 1960-1980s (Boxes 1-2), Fay Franklin Thomas-Vaden Papers, 1934-1944 (Boxes 1- 2), White Caps: Virginia Baptist Hospital Yearbook (Box 1), Helen Yura Papers (Boxes 1-2).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by subcollection.
Contents List
- CNHI: Associations of State & Territorial Directors of Nursing Papers 1985-2001, 4 boxes, 1.75 linear feet
  The materials in this collection consist of administrative documents generated by ASTDN, including correspondence, reports, meeting minutes, bylaws, newsletters, and historical data. The early years of the organization are not represented in the collection, which dates from 1985, although a historical summary dating back to 1935 is included. The ASTDN Papers document the expanding activities and agenda of the organization, as it has acted as an agent in shaping the role and status of the public health nurse.
  The collection has been arranged into three series, reflecting the administrative structure and activities of the organization: Series 1: Administrative: By laws, membership lists, meeting minutes and reports. Series 2: Correspondence and related documents: Series 3: Publications and reports, by ASTDN and other organizations ASTDN, cont'd.
  - Series 1: Administrative: By laws, membership lists, meeting minutes and reports.
    - ASTDN Historical Summary 1935-1993 (Box-folder 001-001)
    - By-laws 1990, 2000 (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: By-laws and policy and procedure manuals.
    - Annual Meetings 1985-1991 (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Programs, minutes and associated documents.
    - Annual Meetings 1991-1995 (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: Programs, minutes and associated documents
    - Annual Meetings 1998-2000 (Box-folder 001-005)
    - Executive Board Meetings 1987-1993 (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Minutes and associated documents.
    - Executive Board Meetings 1994-2000 (Box-folder 001-007)
    - President's Reports 1990-2001 (Box-folder 001-008)
    - Treasurer's Reports 1987-1999 (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: Reports and related financial documents.
    - Committee Reports 1988-1991 (Box-folder 001-010)
    - Committee Reports 1992-2000 (Box-folder 001-011)
    - Member Directories 1989-2000 (Box-folder 001-012)
    - Membership Lists 1992, [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-013)
    - Officers and Committees 1990-1994, [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-014)
    - State Reports to ASTDN 1990-1994 (Box-folder 002-001)
    - State Reports to ASTDN 1995-1996 (Box-folder 002-002)
    - State Reports to ASTDN (Box-folder 002-003)
    - Correspondence: Internal 1989-1990 (Box-folder 002-004)
      Re: Correspondence and related documents re miscellaneous business.
    - Correspondence: Internal 1991-1992 (Box-folder 002-005)
      Re: Correspondence and related documents re miscellaneous ASTDN business
    - Correspondence: Internal 1993 (Box-folder 002-006)
      Re: Correspondence and related documents re miscellaneous ASTDN business.
    - Correspondence: Internal 1995-1997, [n.d.] (Box-folder 002-007)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence: External 1989-1992 (Box-folder 002-008)
      Re: Representatives to ASTDN, meetings, conferences, inter-agency relations.
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence: External 1993-June, 1994 (Box-folder 002-009)
      Re: Meetings, conferences, membership, inter-agency relations, position statements on public health policy.
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence: External July-December, 1994 (Box-folder 002-010)
      Re: Meetings, conferences, membership, inter-agency relations, public health nursing policy.
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence: External January-June, 1995 (Box-folder 002-011)
      Re: Meetings, membership, inter-agency relations, ASTDN goals.
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence: External July-December, 1995 (Box-folder 002-012)
      Re: Meetings, inter-agency relations, public health nurse role.
    - Correspondence: ANA, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 002-013)
      Re:Conferences, Nursing Organization Liason Forum (NOLF), public health nursing policy and practice.
    - Correspondence: ANA 1994 (Box-folder 002-014)
      Re: Meetings, NOLF, public health nursing policy.
    - Correspondence: ANA 1995 (Box-folder 002-015)
  - Series 1: Correspondence; Publications and Reports
    - Correspondence and related documents: Association of State and Territorial Health Officials (ASTHO) 1989-June, 1994 (Box-folder 003-001)
      Re: Health Security Act, ASTHO officers and representatives, school health.
    - Correspondence and related documents: ASTHO July-December, 1994 (Box-folder 003-002)
      Re: Officers, meetings, interns, school health, organizational analysis, public health leadership.
    - Correspondence and related documents: ASTHO 1995, n.d. (Box-folder 003-003)
      Re: Affiliate activities, primary care, mission statement, meetings, health programs, school health, legislative priorities.
    - Correspondence and related documents: ASTHO 1993, n.d. (Box-folder 003-003A)
      Re: Affiliate manual, Association of Health Facility Survey Agencies guide.
    - Correspondence and related documents: Division of Nursing 1992-1995 (Box-folder 003-004)
      Re: Meeting, Division of Nursing report, advice to ASTDN.
    - Correspondence and related documents: Quad Council 1993-1994 (Box-folder 003-005)
      Re: Meetings, policy statements.
    - Correspondence and related documents: Quad Council 1994 (Box-folder 003-006)
      Re: Program of meeting.
    - Correspondence and related documents: Quad Council 1995-1997 (Box-folder 003-007)
    - Correspondence and related documents: Council on Linkages 1994-1995 (Box-folder 003-008)
      Re: Linkages between academic institutions, state and local health departments.
    - Correspondence and related documents: Other Organizations (Box-folder 003-009)
      Re: Public health, nurse executives, TB nurse coalition.
    - Publications and Reports: ASTDN Newsletters 1985-1997 (Box-folder 003-010)
    - Publications and Reports: Compilation of Selected Association Actions (Box-folder 003-011)
      Re: ASTDN resolutions, position papers.
    - Publications and Reports 1990,1994 (Box-folder 003-012)
      ASTDN State Health Departments Nursing Survey, A Study of Public Health Nurse Directors in State Health Departments
  - Series 4: Publications and Reports
    - Publications and Reports July 20-31, 1993; December 2, 1996 (Box-folder 004-001)
      A Nursing Specialist's Delegation to Russia and Estonia, Association Response to Pew Health Professions Commission Report
    - Publications and Reports October 27, 1997 (Box-folder 004-002)
      Re: Public Health Nursing: A Partner for Progress.
    - Publications and Reports 2000 (Box-folder 004-003)
      Re: Public Health Nursing: A Partner for Healthy Populations
    - Publications and Reports 1998-1999 (Box-folder 004-004)
      Re: Video broadcast on role of public health nurse.
    - Publications and Reports 1998-1999 (Box-folder 004-005)
    - Publications and Reports Wald-Trek initiative reports and meetings (Box-folder 004-006)
    - Publications and Reports 1993-1996 (Box-folder 004-007)
      Re: Postcard sketch of public health nursing: state histories and directors
    - Publications and Reports 1997 (Box-folder 004-008)
      Re: 50 Years at the Division of Nursing, USPHS, Reaching for Excellence: The American Public Health Association
    - Publications and Reports 1996 (Box-folder 004-009)
      Re: LaVohn Josten, Population-Focused, Community Oriented Nursing.
- CNHI: Evelyn Crary Bacon Papers 1943-1991, 2 boxes, .8 linear feet
  Evelyn Crary Bacon was born in Iowa in 1916 and earned baccalaureate and master's de-grees from the University of Iowa School of Nursing in 1937 and 1940. From 1942 to 1945 she served in the Army Nurse Corps in the USA and in England, then taught at UCLA and the University of Iowa before enrolling in a doctoral program at the University of Chicago in 1949. Before completing her degree she married Franklin Bacon and moved to Charlottesville, Virginia, where she taught extension courses throughout the state for UVA's Cabaniss School of Nursing Education. She served as acting chair of the University's Department of Nursing Education from 1954 to 1956, then joined the faculty of the Medical College of Virginia School of Nursing in 1960. From 1965 to 1968 Bacon headed the Richmond Professional Institute and during the 1970s and 80s she taught at a number of institutions and was in demand as a consultant. Throughout her career in the state she was a recognized leader in Virginia nursing education, known for her work with the Virginia State Board of Nursing (VSBN), the Virginia Nurses Association (VNA), the Virginia League for Nursing (VLN), and the Southern Regional Education Board. Bacon was also active in the National League for Nursing (NLN). In 1985 she retired from the faculty of the J.S. Reynolds Community College in Richmond
  Because the collection presents no clearly defined structure, it has been arranged into one roughly chronological series from 1942 through 1991. Related topical materials have been combined. This is not a comprehensive collection of Bacon's papers, but a fragmented assortment representing various phases of her personal and professional life between 1942 and 1985. Most of the collection comprises reprints, course outlines, references, and guides, with some correspondence and minutes from meetings of the VSBN and the VNA. Her career from 1955 to 1991 is highlighted in documents relating to the Richmond Professional Institute, the Medical College of Virginia, state boards, nurses associations, and junior colleges, as well as the National League for Nursing and the American Nurses Association. The material is most notable for its World War II correspondence, and for an interview of Bacon discussing her war experiences on cassette tape.
  - 1942-1982
    - US Army Nurse Corps Materials 1942-1967; 1994 (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: Mimeographed personal letters, 1942-45; V-Mail personal letters, 1943-44; Memoir of a visit to "Gay Paree," 1944; Army Nurse Corps brochure,1947; Reunion of WWII Veterans - 25th Anniversary, 1967; taped interview.
    - NLN - BS and Higher Degree Programs 1952-1967 (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: Materials from the NLN to member institutions regarding baccalaureate and higher degree nursing education, including curriculum, evaluation, accreditation, federal support, etc.
    - NLN - Curriculum Conference 1958 (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Conference program, bibliography, related materials.
    - Evaluation of clinical performance 1959-1962 and [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: Notes, reprints on evaluation of clinical performance
    - Legalities and Nursing 1962-1982 (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: Reprints of ANA, other articles on legal aspects of nursing; correspondence, notes, and related materials from a 1981 lecture on the topic by Bacon at Henrico Hospital.
    - Teaching: Improvement of Instruction 1964-1970 and [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Notes, bibliographies, instructional materials from a course.
    - Miscellaneous Virginia Nursing Organizations and State Committees 1956-1976 (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: Correspondence, notes, meeting minutes for VNA, VLN; journal article on history of VNA; Virginia Senate Bill establishing nursing scholarships; letter re Advisory Council on Nursing Training; minutes of Committee on Status of Women.
    - Virginia Public Health Association 1966-1972 (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: Newsletter, historical news article, minutes of nursing group.
    - Virginia Nurses' Association 1957-1971 (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: Meeting minutes, historical articles, correspondence and documents related to 1969 conference.
    - Southern Regional Education Board, Deans' Conference 1968-1969 (Box-folder 001-010)
      Re: Correspondence, documents, and notes related to conferences.
    - Papers by Bacon 1967-1970 (Box-folder 001-011)
      Re: Curriculum development, change, health professions in higher education
    - UVA - McLeod Hall Dedication Program 1972 (Box-folder 001-012)
      Re: Dedication programs, presentation of independent studies program, Sigma Theta Tau installation speech draft.
    - Course: The Nature of Nursing 1973 (Box-folder 001-013)
      Re: Course materials for basic nursing course (taught by Bacon?).
    - Credentialing and Scope of Practice 1974-1978 (Box-folder 001-014)
      Re: Materials on advanced practice nursing, physician's assistants, credentialing health manpower.
  - 1972-1991
    - Primary Care Nursing 1977-1978 (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: Course materials, papers on primary care nursing (taught by Bacon?).
    - Virginia State Board of Nursing: Standards of Practice 1964-1981 (Box-folder 002-002)
      Re: Documents related to Bacon's role as consultant in determining Virginia standards of nursing practice.
    - Licensing of Nurses in Virginia 1968-1980 (Box-folder 002-003)
      Re: Miscellaneous materials related to licensure, certification.
    - Piedmont State Hospital 1976 (Box-folder 002-004)
      Re: Documents related to Virginia Board of Nursing consultation on staff issue.
    - Virginia Psychiatric Hospital Regulations 1976-1980 (Box-folder 002-005)
      Re: Documents related to Virginia Board of Nursing consultations on patient care issues.
    - Nursing Ethics 1979-1981 (Box-folder 002-006)
      Re: Documents related to Bacon guest lecture on ethics at UVA.
    - Piedmont Geriatric Hospital 1979 (Box-folder 002-007)
      Re: Documents related to Bacon consultation visit.
    - Geriatric Nursing Assistant Program 1980 (Box-folder 002-008)
      Re: Report, related documents of VA Geriatric Aide Training Task Force.
    - Papers Critiqued by Bacon 1977-1980 (Box-folder 002-009)
      Re: Papers on sanitarian aide training, program evaluation sent to Bacon for comment.
    - Virginia League for Nursing 1986-1991 (Box-folder 002-010)
      Re: Minutes, correspondence, related documents from VLN.
    - VNA, VLN Archives at Virginia Commonwealth University 1983-1991 (Box-folder 002-011)
      Re: Correspondence, documents related to establishment of VNA, VLN archives at Virginia Commonwealth University.
    - Medical Sociology Course 1986 (Box-folder 002-012)
      Re: Documents related to guest lecture by Bacon.
    - Virginia Schools of Nursing [n.d.] (Box-folder 002-013)
      Re: Lists of Virginia nursing programs.
    - History of Clinical Nursing [n.d.] (Box-folder 002-014)
      Re: Manuscript by unknown author on history of clinical nursing.
    - Miscellaneous ANA, NLN 1966-1982 (Box-folder 002-015)
      Re: ANA response to NCN report, statement on community planning for nursing education.
- CNHI: Alice Burford Booth Papers 1940-1967, 2 boxes, .8 linear feet
  Alice Burford Booth, RN, graduated from Blackstone College in 1940 and from the diploma program in nursing at the Medical College of Virginia (MCV) in 1943. In 1944 she received the bachelor of science in nursing from MCV, based on her course work at other institutions. From 1943 to 1944 she was head nurse on the psychiatric unit, then moved to New York City for post-graduate studies. Returning to MCV in 1945 as clinical instructor in psychiatry, by 1948 she had been promoted to associate professor of psychiatric nursing. After a career hiatus, she returned to MCV from 1965-1967 as instructor in psychiatric nursing in the associate degree program, which closed in 1967, then worked in the Student Health Department at MCV until her retirement in 1982.
  The Burford Booth collection consists primarily of lecture notes, exams and educational pamphlets related to mental health and psychiatry (1940-1960), and curriculum guides for MCV. It comprises psychiatric nursing material from her days as a student and from her career as an instructor. Of some note are two 1944 letters from Johns Hopkins Hospital and Traverse City State Hospital regarding "electroshock convulsion syndrome;" pamphlets on depression, alcoholism, mental hygiene and adjunct therapies in the burgeoning field of psychiatric nursing; and the histories of Eastern State, Central State (Va.) and St. Elizabeth's Hospital in Washington, D.C., and of the Virginia Treatment Center for Children. The papers are a useful source of information on medical treatment of the mentally ill in the World War II era, and on changing attitudes toward mental illness in the medical community and society at large.
  This collection has been arranged into one largely chronological series.
  - 1940-47 and 1965-67
    - Pre-clinical notes and lectures from the MCV Diploma Program (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: History of Nursing, Nursing Arts, Professional Adjustments, Psychology, Anatomy, Emergency Nursing.
    - (Continuation of Folder 1) (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: Bacteriology, Blood and Circulation, Pharmacology, Weights and Measures, Endocrinology, Chemistry.
    - Combination of psychiatric nursing notes from BSN Program and postgraduate studies (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Psychiatric Nursing, Curriculum Guide, Hydrotherapy, Electro Shock Therapy, Ward Manual, Brochures-Depression
    - Course outlines, quizzes and exams from the psychiatric nursing component of the AD Program (Box-folder 001-004)
      Re: Course Outlines, Ward Teaching Program, Physician's Lectures, Insulin Therapy, Mental Hygiene, Midterm and Final Exams, Reference Lists.
    - (Continuation of Folder 4) (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: Course Outlines, Principles of Psychiatric Nursing, Attitudes, Nurse-Patient Relationships, Interviewing, Roles and Functions, Quizzes and Exams.
    - (Continuation of Folder 5) (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Course Outlines, Evaluations, Rehabilitation, Exams, Bibliographies, Reference Lists, Films.
  - 1940-47 and 1965-67
    - Teaching materials and pamphlets on adjunct therapies (Box-folder 002-001)
      Re: Schedules and Orientation, ECT, Insulin Coma Therapy, Alcoholism, Psychology Outline, Reports, St. Elizabeth's Hospital, Lynchburg Training School, Central State Hospital, Mental Illness.
    - Continuation of Folder 1 (Box-folder 002-002)
      Re: History of Care, Mental Health, Religious Needs, Legal Aspects, Student Evaluations, Pamphlets on Tension.
    - Teaching materials (Box-folder 002-003)
      Re: Tests and Quizzes, Mid-term and Final Exams.
    - MCV School of Nursing curriculum materials (Box-folder 002-004)
    - Assorted pamphlets and journals (Box-folder 002-005)
      Re: Mental Health
    - Assorted pamphlets and journals (Box-folder 002-006)
    - Assorted pamphlets and journals (Box-folder 002-007)
- Dr. Barbara Brodie Papers 1955-1975, 1 box, .4 linear feet
  Follows school of nursing history in hospitals and schools of practical nursing throughout Virginia.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - School of Nursing History
    - Alexandria Hospital 1959-1967 (Box-folder 001-001)
      Re: History.
    - Blue Ridge Sanatorium 1958 (Box-folder 001-002)
      Re: Typed History: 1920-1958.
    - Chesapeake & Ohio Hospital, Clifton Forge, VA 1966 (Box-folder 001-003)
      Re: Bulletin of the School of Nursing.
    - Community Hospital of Roanoke Valley 1965-1970 (Box-folder 001-004)
    - De Paul Hospital, Norfolk, VA 1967 (Box-folder 001-005)
      Re: Historical Statement.
    - Eastern Mennonite College 1966 (Box-folder 001-006)
      Re: Bulletin & Brochures.
    - Germanna Community College, Fredericksburg, VA [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-007)
      Re: Loose pages with "General Information".
    - Grace Hospital Richmond, VA 1969-70 (Box-folder 001-008)
      Re: Typed Historical Background, 1911-1963.
    - Hampton Institute 1963-1970 (Box-folder 001-009)
      Re: Student handbook, history or nursing.
    - Hampton Training School 1955 (Box-folder 001-010)
      Re: Typed History 1891-1956, memo and correspondence regarding closing.
    - Jefferson Hospital, Roanoke, Va. 1967 (Box-folder 001-011)
      Re: Historical Information, 1914-1965.
    - John Tyler Community College [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-012)
      Re: Printed loose pages.
    - Johnston Memorial Hospital, Abingdon, Va. [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-013)
    - Johnston-Willis Hospital, Richmond, Va. [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-014)
      Re: Loose pages from hospital brochure.
    - King's Daughter Hospital, Wilson Memorial High School 1958 (Box-folder 001-015)
      RE: Brief typed history from 1950-58.
    - Lewis-Gale Hospital [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-016)
      Re: Historical information, 1911-1965.
    - Louise Obici Hospital [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-017)
      Re: Printed loose page "history."
    - Mary Immaculate Hospital [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-018)
      Re: Typed history, 1906-1954.
    - Maryview Hospital, Portsmouth, Va. 1958-1970 (Box-folder 001-019)
      Re: Letter & histories.
    - Medical College of Virginia, Richmond, Va. 1965 (Box-folder 001-020)
      Re: 1838-1965 typed time line history.
    - Memorial Hospital, Danville, Va. [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-021)
      Re: Typed history, 1898-1954.
    - Norfolk Division of Virginia State College [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-022)
    - Norfolk General Hospital 1963 (Box-folder 001-023)
      Re: Typed history, 1892-1961.
    - Northern Virginia Community College 1967 (Box-folder 001-024)
      Re: Typed "Historial Data"; 1966-1967.
    - Patrickk Henry College, Martinsville, Va 1070-71 (Box-folder 001-025)
    - Petersburg General Hospital 1955-1968 (Box-folder 001-026)
      Re: Leggers about school & typed history.
    - Piedmont Sanatorium, Burkeville, Va. 1958 (Box-folder 001-027)
      Re: Typed History: 1918-1958.
    - Portsmouth General Hospital 1958-66 (Box-folder 001-028)
      Re: Typed history: 1904-1942.
    - Richmond Memorial Hospital 1961-1968 (Box-folder 001-029)
      Re: Newspaper photos & typed historical data.
    - Riverside Hospital 1968 (Box-folder 001-030)
      Re: Typed history, 1916-1968.
    - Roanoake Memorial Hospital [n.d.] (Box-folder 001-031)
      Re: Loose pages.
    - Rockingham Memorial Hospital 1970 (Box-folder 001-032)